Guide to the Gordon and Brysis Whitnall papers, 1913-1975
Whitnall, Gordon and Brysis papers, 1913-1975
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gordon and Brysis Whitnall papers, 1913-1975
2880
Gordon Whitnall, 1888-1977.
22.6 cubic ft., 12 tape recordings, 9 transcripts.
Ordinances, maps, reports, correspondence, course outlines, interview tapes and transcript, publications, family and biographical material, income tax returns; and other miscellaneous business and personal papers.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Contains material on Gordon and Brysis Whitnall's careers as planners as well as family and biographical records.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
In 1913, Gordon Whitnall founded the Los Angeles City Planning Association, and in 1920, he established the Los Angeles City Planning Department. From 1920-1930, he was Director of Planning for Los Angeles, and from 1929-1930 was president of the League of California Cities. From 1932-1935 he was the coordinator of the Committee on Government Simplification for Los Angeles County. In 1941, Gordon and Brysis Whitnall established a planning and government consulting firm in Los Angeles. Gordon Whitnall was an instructor in Planning at the University of Southern California, and a member of the American Society of Planning Officials, the American Institute of Planners, the American Society of Consulting Planners, and the International Fraternity of Lambda Alpha, Los Angeles Chapter.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes ordinances, maps, reports, and correspondence for cities in the West and Southwest, including Amarillo, Texas; Albuquerque, New Mexico; Seattle, Washington; and Los Angeles, Modesto, Glendale, Palm Springs, and numerous other cities in California. Personal files consist of course outlines; Gordon and Brysis Whitnall interview tapes and transcript; material on Charles B. Whitnall Park; professional society correspondence, publications, and research information concerning the American Institute of Planners, the American Society of Planning Officials, and other organizations; published articles and reports; and tape recording of a speech at Cornell University, "After a Half Century of Urban Zoning - What's the Verdict." Also, family and biographical material; income tax returns; and other miscellaneous business and personal papers.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Whitnall, Gordon, 1888-1977.; Whitnall, Brysis.; American Institute of Planners.; American Society of Consulting Planners.; American Society of Planning Officials.; League of California Cities.; Los Angeles California City Planning Association.; Los Angeles California City Planning Department.; Los Angeles County California Committee on Government Simplification.; University of Southern California School of Architecture.; University of Southern California School of Public Administration.; Lambda Alpha International Los Angeles Chapter.
Subjects:
City planning.; Zoning.; City planners.
Places:
Albuquerque (New Mexico)--City planning.; Amarillo (Texas)--City planning.; Glendale (California)--City planning.; Los Angeles (California)--City planning.; Los Angeles County (California); Modesto (California)--City planning.; Palm Springs (California)--City planning.; Seattle (Washington)--City planning.
Form and Genre Terms:
Interviews.; Maps.; Speeches.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Personal Files
Box 11 and 15
Series II. Ordinances, Maps, Reports, and Correspondence (Alpha and Date Files)
Boxes 1-11; 15-22
Alphabetical File I
Alphabetical File II
Alphabetical File III
Files Arranged By Date
Series III. Professional Societies: Correspondence, Publications, Research Information
Box 12-13
Series IV. Papers by Gordon Whitnall (a few by others)
Box 14
CONTAINER LIST
- Personal Files
  - Gordon and Brysis Whitnall Interviews, c. 1970 (Box 11)
    2 tape recordings, one transcript, trans.??? to appropriate locations
    - Tape recording, Transcript 4545-4546
    - Tape recording, Transcript 4545-4546
  - University of Southern California. Course outlines, planning, c. 1959-1963 (Box 11)
  - Speeches, c. 1968 (Box 11)
  - Christmas Card, photographs, c. 1969 (Box 11)
  - Charles B. Whitnall Par. Hales Corners, Wisconsin, c. 1968 (Box 11)
  - Speech by Charles Whitnall, c. 1937 (Box 11)
  - Whitnall Family Tree (Box 15)
  - Brysis' Affairs (Box 15)
  - Whitnall, Brysis N. (Personal) (Box 15)
  - Whitnall, Byrsis N. (Personal) (Box 15)
  - Whitnal, C.B. (Personal) (Box 15)
  - Whitnal, C.B. (Personal) (Box 15)
  - G.W. Biographical Data (Box 15)
  - 3719 Prestwick Drive (Box 15)
  - Personal Correspondence, unfinished (Box 15)
- Ordinances, Maps, Reports, and Correspondence
  - Alphabetical File I
    - Amarillo, Texas, c. 1952-1963 (Box 1)
    - Albuquerque, New Mexico, c. 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - Alhambra, California, c. 1955-1960 (Box 1)
    - Anaheim, California, c. 1945-1961 (Box 1)
    - Bakersfield, California, c. 1955 (Box 1)
    - Banning, California, c. 1952-1954 (Box 1)
    - Butte County, California, c. 1956-1962 (Box 1)
    - Carlsbad, California, c. 1956-1962 (Box 1)
    - Chula Vista, California, c. 1949-1963 (Box 1)
    - China Lake, California (United States Naval Test Station), c. 1945-1959 (Box 2)
    - Colton, California, c. 1950-1960 (Box 2)
    - Downey, California, c. 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    - El Cajon, California, c. 1953-1959 (Box 2)
    - El Sequndo, California, c. 1947-1963 (Box 2)
    - Exeter, California, c. 1947-1963 (Box 2)
    - Forest Lawn Memorial Park, (Los Angeles County, California), c. 1963 (Box 2)
    - Fresno County, California, c. 1949-1960 (Box 3)
    - Fullerton, California, c. 1947-1967 (Box 3)
    - Garden Grove, California, c. 1956-1961 (Box 4)
    - Glendale, California, c. 1955-1962 (Box 4)
    - Glendora, California, c. 1955-1958 (Box 4)
    - Hawthorne, California, c. 1955, 1961-1963 (Box 4)
    - Indio, California, c. 194-1963 (Box 4)
    - Inglewood, California, c. 1952 (Box 4)
    - Kings County, California, c. 1946-1963 (Box 5)
    - Kings County, Washington, c. 1954-1964 (Box 6)
    - Los Angeles, California, c. 1925, 1931-1964 (Box 7)
    - Los Angeles County, California, c. 1931, 1951-1961 (Box 7)
    - Laguna Beach, California, 1939-1955 (Box 7)
    - La Mesa, California, 1945-1954 (Box 7)
    - La Puente, California, c. 1956-1957 (Box 7)
    - Manhattan Beach, California, c. 1954-1962 (Box 8)
    - Merced, California, c. 1949-1956 (Box 8)
    - Modesto, California, c. 1943, 1953-1961 (Box 8)
    - Montebello, California, c. 1954-1958 (Box 8)
    - Oceanside, California, c. 1949-1962 (Box 8)
    - Orange County, California, c. 1957-1964 (Box 8)
    - Palm Springs, California, c. 1951-1956 (Box 9)
    - Paramount, California, c. 1958-1962 (Box 9)
    - Pismo Beach, California, c. 1955-1960 (Box 9)
    - Pomona, California, c. 1946 (Box 9)
    - Porterville, California, c. 1949-1962 (Box 9)
    - Reedley, California, c. 1948-1956 (Box 9)
    - Redondo Beach, California, c. 1948-1950, 1955 (Box 9)
    - San Diego County, California, c. 1946-1960 (Box 9)
    - Sanger, California, c. 1942, 1949-1955 (Box 10)
    - Selma, California, c. 1948-1956 (Box 10)
    - Sierra Madre, California, c. 1953-1963 (Box 10)
    - Southgate, California, c. 1957-1961 (Box 10)
    - Temple City, California, c. 1960-1964 (Box 10)
    - Tulare County, California, c. 1946-1956 (Box 11)
    - Ventura, California, c. 1947-1956 (Box 11)
    - West Covina, California, c. 1952-1956 (Box 11)
    - Whittier, California, c. 1930, 1954-1958 (Box 11)
    - Woodlake, California, c. 1950-1952 (Box 11)
  - Alphabetical File II
    - American Institute of Planners, 1944, 1945 (Box 15)
    - Scholarship Fund California Chapter - A.I.P. (Box 15)
    - [A.I.P] California Planners Foundation Scholarship Fund (Box 15)
    - Anaheim, City of (Box 15)
    - A.S.C.P. (Box 15)
    - Board File A.S.C.P., 1967 (Box 15)
    - Compton Ordinance Review (Box 15)
    - Compton - William F. Hill (Box 15)
    - Contracts - Insurance Policies (Box 15)
    - Cornell University - John M. Olin Research Library (Box 15)
    - Domingues Hills State College (Box 15)
    - Franchise Tax (Box 15)
    - Fresno County Planning Commission (Box 15)
    - Fresno - "Off - Street Parking" (Box 16)
    - GAG - Government Administration Group (Box 16)
    - Glendale, City of (Box 16)
    - Griffith Advisory Committee (Box 16)
    - Griffith Park (Box 16)
    - History - Planning and Zoning (Box 16)
    - Incubator (Box 16)
    - Los Angeles Metropolitan History Project (Box 16)
    - Los Angeles General Plan (concept) (Box 16)
    - Lambda Alpha - Board and Committee (Box 16)
    - Mass-transit (Box 16)
    - Milwaukee Baby Bonds (Box 16)
    - Moorfield (Box 16)
    - Edward W. Nettles, Planning 501 (Box 16)
    - Palm Springs (Box 16)
    - Paramount (Box 16)
    - Ryan vs. County of Riverside (Box 16)
    - Temple City - Zoning Ordinance (Box 16)
    - Temple City - Landfill Survey (Box 16)
    - U.S.C. 636 - Fall, 1971 (Box 16)
    - U.S.C. Spring Term, 1972 (Box 16)
  - Alphabetical File III
    - "A" (Box 17)
    - "A", 1944 (Box 17)
    - Air Raid and Post Material (Box 17)
    - A.S.C.P. HUD-DOT etc. (Box 17)
    - A.S.P.O. - Blucher (Box 17)
    - Atlanta, Georgia (Box 17)
    - "B" (Box 17)
    - Better Roads - Curtis Fuller (Box 17)
    - "C" (Box 17)
    - "C", 1944 (Box 17)
    - California Housing and Plan Association (Box 17)
    - Clark, Fred P., New Hampshire (Box 17)
    - Christmas Valley - Records of case heard by California Real Estate Commissioners (Box 17)
    - "D" (Box 17)
    - "D", 1944 (Box 17)
    - Daly, Thos.??? P. (Box 17)
    - Downtown Survey U.L.I.???, 1942 (Box 17)
    - "E" (Box 17)
    - "E", 1944 (Box 17)
    - Eighth and Vermont Avenue Project (Box 17)
    - Equitable and Various Finances (Box 17)
    - Eminent Domain (Box 17)
    - "F" (Box 17)
    - "F" (Box 17)
    - Fresno City (Box 17)
    - County of Fresno (Box 17)
    - Fresno County, 1942 (Box 17)
    - Fresno County No. 2, 1943 (Box 17)
    - Fresno County, 1944 (Box 17)
    - Fresno County, 1945 (Box 17)
    - "G" (Box 17)
    - Gilmore Island (Box 17)
    - Gilmore Island Project, Raymond Haight (Box 17)
    - Glendale, City of (Box 17)
    - "H" (Box 17)
    - "H" (Box 17)
    - Haynes Fountain and T.H. Plan. Sec.??? (Box 17)
    - Humphreys Bros., Miles O. Humphreys (Box 17)
    - Income Tax Returns (Box 17)
    - Income Tax Returns (Box 17)
    - Income Tax Returns (Box 17)
    - "J" (Box 18)
    - "J" (Box 18)
    - Patty Railsback Kennedy (Box 18)
    - Kids Affairs (Box 18)
    - "L" (Box 18)
    - "L" (Box 18)
    - Lafayette Park Place (Box 18)
    - Leimert Pk. - Beverly Woof Oil Study (Box 18)
    - Leimert, Walter H. (Box 18)
    - Limited Access Highways, 1951 (Box 18)
    - Long Beach, City of (Box 18)
    - "M" (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
    - "M" Miscellaneous (Box 18)
    - MacDonald Zoning Case (Box 18)
    - Maier, Edw.??? J., Newark, N.J. (Box 18)
    - Military Government School - Commission (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous Personal and Business (Box 18)
    - "N" (Box 18)
    - "N" (Box 18)
    - National Association of Real Estate Boards (N.A.R.E.B.) (Box 18)
    - National Association of Real Estate Boards (N.A.R.E.B.) (Box 18)
    - "O" (Box 18)
    - Off - Street Parking (Box 18)
    - Oneonta - Page M.A.??? (Box 18)
    - Oneonta - Page (Box 18)
    - Oxnard, City of (Box 18)
    - "P" (Box 18)
    - "P" (Box 18)
    - Pacific Western Oil Company (Box 18)
    - Pasadena Survey (Box 18)
    - Pending Projects (Box 18)
    - Personal (Box 18)
    - Portland, Oregon (Box 18)
    - "R" (Box 18)
    - Receipts, 1944 (Box 18)
    - Receipts, 1945 (Box 18)
    - Receipts, 1948 (Box 18)
    - "S" (Box 18)
    - "S" (Box 18)
    - Santa Ana - Irvin Chapman (Box 18)
    - Santa Monica, City of (Box 18)
    - Seaboard (Box 18)
    - Seattle - Washington (Box 18)
    - "T" (Box 19)
    - Todell, Ellen, Estate, Miscellaneous (Box 19)
    - Town Hall (Box 19)
    - Town Hall (Box 19)
    - Town Hall (Box 19)
    - Town Hall (Box 19)
    - Town Hall (Box 19)
    - Town Hall No. 2 (Box 19)
    - Trust Fund - Farmers and Merchant Bank (Box 19)
    - "U" (Box 19)
    - Upland, City of (Box 19)
    - U.L.I. - Chas. T. Stewart, 1942 (Box 19)
    - Urban Land Institute - Seward Mott (Box 19)
    - Urban Redevelopment Legislation File #1 (Box 19)
    - Urban Redevelopment Legislation File #2 (Box 19)
    - U.S.C. Fall Semester 501, 1970 (Box 19)
    - U.S.C. Fall, 1970 (Box 19)
    - "V" (Box 19)
    - "V" (Box 19)
    - Vaega Aircraft Corporation Fresno (Box 19)
    - Visalia Inc., 1940-1942 (Box 19)
    - Visalia, 1943-1945 (Box 19)
    - War Training Program (Box 19)
    - Whittier - Kemmerer (Box 19)
    - "W" (Box 19)
    - Zoning Ordinance Revision, Los Angeles (Box 19)
    - Zoning and Planning, 1964, 1965 (Box 19)
  - Filed by Date
    - Business Papers and Correspondence, 1938-1968 (Box 20)
    - Business Papers and Correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 21)
    - Printed Material (Box 21)
    - Printed Material, 1964-1974 (Box 22)
    - Undated Material (Box 22)
- Professional Societies: Correspondence, Publications, Research Information
  - American Planing and Civic Association, c. 1957-1963 (Box 12)
  - American Institute of Planners, c. 1961-1963 (Box 12)
  - American Society of Planning Officials, c. 1957-1963 (Box 12)
  - Planning Advisory Service (ASPO), c. 1955-1962 (Box 12)
  - Southern California Hospital Planning Region, c. 1960-1962 (Box 12)
  - Town Hall, Inc. Los Angeles, California, c. 1931-1936 (Box 12)
  - Urban Renewal (Redevelopment), c. 1941-1961 (Box 12)
  - Research material. California, etc. Conservation, Planning, Zoning, c. 1934-1964 (Box 12)
  - 33 volumes. PLANNING. Selected Papers from the annual National Planning Conference. American Society of Planning Officials, c.1913; 1925-1967 (Box 13)
- Papers by Gordon Whitnall (a few by others)
  - General Observations and Citizens on the Planning Program and Procedures of the City of El Paso, Texas, May 1959 (Box 14)
  - Seattle Cityscape by Victor Steinbrueck, 1962 (Box 14)
  - Master Plan of Streets and Highways, City of El Ca Jon, California, 1954 (Box 14)
  - Master Plan of Off - Street Parking, City of El Ca Jon, California, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Community Development Plan. A report on the elements of a master plan, 1957 (Box 14)
  - Industrial Site Analysis, Anaheim, California, 1950 (Box 14)
  - Report on Land Use Analysis. Prepared for 3475 investments, Mar. 1964 (Box 14)
  - Report on Master Plan, City of Indio, California, 1954 (Box 14)
  - Proper Use of Variance, 1957 (Box 14)
  - Are Building Line Setbacks Valid, 1952 (Box 14)
  - Street and Highway Element of a Master Plan, Whittier, California, 1955 (Box 14)
  - A Comprehensive General Plan. Garden Grove, California, 1958 (Box 14)
  - Master Plan of the City of Fullerton, California, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Report on Proposed Comprehensive General Plan of Temple, California, 1963 (Box 14)
  - Report on Proposed Comprehensive General Plan of Hawthorne, California, 1963 (Box 14)
  - Franklin Bills. Yule Springs Park, Las Vegas, Nevada, 1967 (Box 14)
  - Zoning Reclassification of a Portion of "C" Street Frontage in Chula Vista, California (Box 14)
  - Off - Street Parking, Tulane, California, 1950 (Box 14)
  - Proposed Master Plan for United States Naval Ordinance Test Station, China Lake, California (Box 14)
  - Techniques of Design for Off - Street Parking Facilities, Los Angeles, California, 1947 (Box 14)
  - Kit Carson Park, Escondido, California, 1968 (Box 14)
  - Manhattan Beach, California, 1959 (Box 14)
  - Report Master Plan City of La Mesa, California, 1954 (Box 14)
  - Community Development Plan, Montebello, California, 1956 (Box 14)
  - Report on Comprehensive General Plan, Oceanside, California, 1957 (Box 14)
  - Pismo Beach, Freeway Alignment, Analysis and Findings, 1955 (Box 14)
  - "Five Points" Area El Monte Vicinity, August 1955 (Box 14)
  - Report on proposed comprehensive General Plan for South Gate, California, 1959 (Box 14)
  - Survey of Use Potential, 1934 (Box 14)
  - Off - Street Parking Study, City Planning Commission, 1946 (Box 14)
  - A Program to Improve Planning and Zoning in Los Angeles, July 1968 (Box 14)
  - Marlesta Shopping Center, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Washington State Planning Law, 1959 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender & Company, Inc. Institute on Planning and Zoning. No. 1. Dallas, Texas (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender & Company, Inc. Institute on Planning and Zoning. No. 2. Dallas, Texas, 1962 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender & Company, Inc. Institute on Planning and Zoning. No. 3. Dallas, Texas, 1963 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender & Company, Inc. Institute on Planning and Zoning. No. 4. Dallas, Texas, 1964 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender & Company, Inc. Institute on Planning and Zoning. No. 5. Dallas, Texas, 1965 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender & Company, Inc. Institute on Planning and Zoning. No. 6. Dallas, Texas, 1966 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender & Company, Inc. Institute on Planning and Zoning. No. 7. Dallas, Texas, 1967 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender & Company, Inc. Institute on Planning and Zoning. No. 8. Dallas, Texas, 1969 (Box 14)
  - Your Guide to Osaka. Commerce and Industry Dept., Osaka (Box 14)
  - New Concepts in Planning 7 Zoning, 1963 (Box 14)
  - Floor Space Requirements and Civic Center Plan, Barstow, California, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Streets and Highways Element of a Master Plan, Manhattan Beach, California, 1956 (Box 14)
  - Parking Survey for the City of Oceanside, California, 1952 (Box 14)
  - Tulane County Planning Commission, 1951 (Box 14)
  - Redevelopment Authority Project, 1952 (Box 14)
  - City of Laguna Beach, California, 1954 (Box 14)
  - City of Indic, California, 1954 (Box 14)
  - City of Colton, 1953 (Box 14)
  - Streets and Highways, 1952 (Box 14)
  - Downey City School and Planning Commission, 1963 (Box 14)
  - Industrial Area Study for El Segundo, 1951 (Box 14)
  - Off Street Parking for Salt Lake City, 1953 (Box 14)
  - Modern Shopping Center, 1951 (Box 14)
  - Administrative Survey, 1950 (Box 14)
  - Problem of Cities and Towns by Guy Greer, 1942 (Box 14)
  - The Simplification of Modern Government by George H. Dunlop, 1937 (Box 14)
  - Planning of the Cities, Towns and Villages by John Nolen, 1919 (Box 14)
  - Laws Relating to the State of California, 1966 (Box 14)
  - Department of Community Affairs, Jefferson City, Urban Planning Assistance Guide, 1967 (Box 14)
  - Conditions Attached to Planning and Zoning by Brysis N, Whitnall, 1965 (Box 14)
  - Dallas Citizens. Goals for Dallas, 1969 (Box 14)
  - Five Lectures in Planning by C.B. Whitnall, 1937 (Box 14)
  - Tulane County Planning Commission. Road and House Numbering, 1951 (Box 14)
  - King's County and Hanford City Planning Commission, Joint Point for Public Building Sites, 1953 (Box 14)
  - Planning and Government, 1950 (Box 14)
  - Off - Street Parking Study, 1946 (Box 14)
  - Plan for Vancouver, British Columbia by Harland Bartholomew, 1928 (Box 14)
  - How to place color on land use maps, 1963 (Box 14)
  - Committee on Governmental Simplification, 1935 (Box 14)
  - Redevelopment Authority Project, 1952 (Box 14)
  - Stratmore Hearing, 1951 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender Company 1961, Institute on Planning and Zoning, 1962 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender Company Eighth Annual Institute on Planning and Zoning, 1970 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender Company 1964, Institute on Planning and Zoning (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender Company Metropolitan Area Planning, 1965 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender Company Extraterritorial Jurisdiction, 1964 (Box 14)
  - Matthew Bender Company 1963 Institute for Planning and Zoning, 1964 (Box 14)
  - International Federation for Housing and Planning, Jerusalem, 1964 (Box 14)